Guide to the Top Value Television papers, 1964-2004 (bulk 1971-1977) 1964-2004 PFA.MSS.008
BAMPFA Film Library
Top Value Television papers
1964-2004
1971-1977
BAMPFA Film Library
Ant Farm (Design group)
Raindance Corporation
TVTV (Production company)
Videofreex (Production company)
Apple, Wendy
Blumberg, Skip
Lord, Chip
Marquez, Hudson
Murray, Bill, 1950 September 21-
Rucker, Allen
Shamberg, Michael
Weinberg, Tom
PFA.MSS.008
4 Cartons, 7 Containers 7.5 linear feet
Correspondence, scripts, budgets, production notes, videotape logs, publications, clippings, artwork, publicity ephemera, scrapbooks. TVTV produced independent television shows that challenged established broadcast media models from1972-1979 in San Francisco and Los Angeles, California. The collection consists of materials generated in the production of the group's shows, papers related to the operation of TVTV Inc., original artwork and publicity materials created by and for TVTV, as well as a self-published booklet and articles written by and about TVTV and its members. Finally, the collection includes similar materials created by TVTV members for productions outside of TVTV. Productions are referenced with all capitalized letters -- e.g., THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO (1972).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Physical access to some materials has been limited due to condition and preservation concerns. Efforts have been made to provide access copies of these materials whenever possible. Please contact the BAMPFA Film Library and Study Center regarding physical access to these materials.
Accruals
Additions are not expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
BAMPFA Video Curator Steve Seid acquired the materials from TVTV members in 2009, 2012, and 2014.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection has been digitized and is available via the UC Berkeley Libraries digital collections system.
Arrangement
Arranged in 5 series, each of which is subdivided into subseries. Series and subseries are arranged in chronological order where applicable, otherwise in order of relevance to the operation of TVTV. Where no original order existed, materials are arranged to reflect the above system.
Series 1: Productions, 1964, 1967, 1972-1979, undated
Series 2: TVTV Corporate Papers & General Correspondence, 1972-1979, 1981, undated
Series 3: Artwork & Related Materials, 1972, 1974, undated
Series 4: Publications, 1972-1976, 1978, 1983, 1997, 2004, undated
Series 5: Side Projects & Post-TVTV, 1975-1979, undated
Biographical / Historical
Top Value Television (TVTV) was founded in 1972 by Michael Shamberg, Megan Williams, and Allen Rucker (with a handful of associated artists) as a guerrilla video collective based in San Francisco, California. The group developed from ties to San Francisco Bay Area and New York City arts collectives such as Ant Farm (of which TVTV co-founders Hudson Marquez, Chip Lord, Curtis Schreier, and Doug Michels were members), Videofreex, and Raindance (of which Shamberg was a member). Independent producers such as Wendy Apple and Paul Goldsmith provided essential technical skills. The group was influential in bridging the gap between 1970s counterculture and broadcast television.
The initial spark for TVTV's formation was a desire to document the 1972 presidential nominating conventions in Miami, Florida, from a point of view that the major television networks would be unable to capture. Small-format video equipment like the Sony Porta-Pak and hand held audio tape recorders offered TVTV the technical freedom to approach the conventions in a way that reflected their counterculture origins. More significantly, their cinéma-vérité-for-the-new-generation challenged the "official" version of events as presented by the established media. Critical attention paid to the two tapes produced at these events legitimized TVTV's efforts and established the group as a presence in alternative television. The combination of technical savvy and a "rock-n-roll" style characterized TVTV's productions for the next seven years, as the organization turned its lens on American institutions including the Superbowl, the Oscars, and the impeachment of Richard Nixon.
In 1975, after having produced several shows with cooperation from public television stations around the country (in particular, New York's WNET and its TV Lab), TVTV left San Francisco for Los Angeles. A tentativedeal with the local Public Broadcasting Service affiliate, KCET, and proximity to Hollywood's network TV establishment provided the group with additional incentive to move on. TVTV produced 13 works that were broadcast on cable networks and PBS, and in 1977 filmed the pilot episode for a show on NBC that would have brought the collective onto national TV. By this point however, tensions between media "insider" and "outsider" status generated disagreements over what direction the group should take, funding became more precarious, and in 1979 the group officially disbanded. TVTV's attempts to bring alternative voices in television into the mainstream reflect a movement that became increasingly marginalized and underfunded by the 1980s and 1990s, but the programs produced by the group remain as documents of a more hopeful moment in alternative television.
During the course of its operations, TVTV members maintained their relationships with other groups involved in alternative video and television. As part of this involvement in the alternative television movement, TVTV (and particularly members Michael Shamberg and Allen Rucker) participated in an effort to bring more underground voices into programming funded by PBS and the National Endowment for the Arts. This "Coalition for New Public Affairs Programming" lobbied Congress, PBS, and the Corporation for Public Broadcasting to include independent programming, including counterculture voices, in its broadcasting agenda.
Following the dissolution of TVTV, members continued to create programming for television, film, and other arts. Megan Williams and Wendy Apple collaborated on mainstream and alternative television projects with each other and with outside groups (including Chicago's Videopolis), with Williams ultimately leaving media production in the 1980s. Allen Rucker went on to a career writing nonfiction books and screenplays. Michael Shamberg had long had associations with the film industry. His roommate at Washington University in St. Louis was Harold Ramis, who became a successful Hollywood director and producer, and other connections brought actors Jim Belushi and Bill Murray into the TVTV fold before they became international celebrities. Ultimately, Shamberg became a successful film and television producer with titles including Pulp Fiction (1994) and episodes of Reno 911! (2004-2008).
General
Finding Aid Author(s):
Michael Campos-Quinn
Date Completed:
August, 2012
Finding Aid Encoded By:
Michael Campos-Quinn
Publication
Top Value Television. (1974). The Prime Time Survey: TV of the Future. San Francisco: TVTV
Bibliography
Anker, S., Geritz, K., & Seid, S. (2010). Radical Light: Alternative Film & Video in the San Francisco Bay Area, 1945-2000. Berkeley: University of California Press.
Boyle, D. (1997). Subject to Change: Guerrilla Television Revisited. New York: Oxford University Press.
Demartino, N. (July 2011). Objectively speaking. Weblog post. Retrieved from http://www.nickdemartino.net/blog/2011/7/4/objectively-speaking.html
IMDB. (2010). Michael Shamberg. Retrieved from http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0787834/
Scope and Contents
The majority of the materials in this collection were generated in the production of TVTV programs and in preparation for potential programs that were not ultimately produced. These include correspondence, financial documents and budgets, research materials for productions, notes made in planning and scripting programs, full and draft treatments, scripts, tape logs, ephemera, marketing collateral and artwork, photos, and production scrapbooks. The collection also contains newspaper and magazine clippings of articles written by and about TVTV, lecture materials prepared by TVTV members for presentations, as well as a publication, The Prime Time Survey, distributed by TVTV in 1974. Also included are materials relating to a 2004 exhibition that featured TVTV, the Museum of Television and Radio's 2004 Television Documentary Festival.
The collection also includes materials that were produced as part of various side projects and productions in which TVTV members participated during the decline of TVTV and after its dissolution in 1979. These are largely similar materials to those produced by TVTV proper. Another significant side project represented here is an alternative television advocacy group that was actively supported by members of TVTV. Correspondence and other materials related to the Coalition for New Public Affairs Programming reflect TVTV's engagement with the group.
Separated Materials
Original master tapes and raw tape footage from TVTV productions were donated to the Pacific Film Archive at the same time as the paper records in this collection. 1/2-inch open-reel, 3/4-inch cassette, 1-inch Type C, and VHS cassette tapes produced by TVTV are kept in the film archive offsite storage. Access to some of these materials is restricted. Please contact the BAMPFA Film Library and Study Center for more information.
Tapes from THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO, FOUR MORE YEARS, and GERALD FORD'S AMERICA have been digitized and are available on the Internet Archive (archive.org).
Experimental films--United States; Documentary films--United States; Video art--California; Public television--United States; Low budget television programs--United States; Political conventions--United States--1970-1980; Rawat, Prem, 1957-; Hoffman, Abbie; Dylan, Bob, 1941-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006
- Series 1: Productions, 1964, 1967, 1972-1979, undated; 57 Folders, 14 Binders
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into 15 subseries.
  Subseries 1: THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO (1972), 1972, 1976
  Subseries 2: FOUR MORE YEARS (1972), 1972
  Subseries 3: Political convention tapes reviews, 1972, undated
  Subseries 4: LORD OF THE UNIVERSE (1974), 1973-1975
  Subseries 5: ADLAND (1974), 1973, undated
  Subseries 6: IN HIDING (1975), 1975, undated
  Subseries 7: GERALD FORD'S AMERICA (1975), 1975
  Subseries 8: THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME (1975), 1974-1975, undated
  Subseries 9: TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL (1976), 1976, undated
  Subseries 10: TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS (1976), 1976-1977, 1983, undated
  Subseries 11: THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL (1976), 1976- 1977, undated
  Subseries 12: SUPER VISION (1976), 1975-1977, undated
  Subseries 13: THE TVTV SHOW (1977), 1975-1977
  Subseries 14: Unrealized projects, 1973-1979, undated
  Subseries 15: Videotape raw shot logs and edit logs, 1974 -1976, undated
  Scope and Contents
  This series, arranged chronologically by material type, comprises the bulk of the collection. It contains materials generated in the production of TVTV's programs, including correspondence, budgets, scripts, working notes, publicity photographs, legal and financial documents, and shot logs from TVTV's raw video footage. Also included are clippings of reviews that relate to specific productions.
  - Subseries 1: THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO (1972), 1972, 1976; 4 Folders
    This subseries consists of correspondence, planning documents, promotional material, press clippings, and photographs related to the production of THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO (1972). The original folder holding the photographs (head shots of various personalities) included two similar, but apparently unrelated, photographs dated 1976 that have been kept in their original order.
    - THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO, correspondence, 1972; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 1)
    - THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO, promotional material, 1972, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 2)
    - THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO, reviews and press clippings, 1972; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 3)
    - THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO, photographs, 1972, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: FOUR MORE YEARS (1972), 1 Folder
    Consists of press clippings of broadcast announcements and reviews related to FOUR MORE YEARS.
    - FOUR MORE YEARS, press clippings, 1972; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Political convention tapes reviews, 1972, undated; 1 Folder
    Consists of press clippings related to both of TVTV's 1972 political convention programs, THE WORLD'S LARGEST TV STUDIO and FOUR MORE YEARS.
    - Political convention tapes reviews, 1972; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 4: LORD OF THE UNIVERSE (1974), 1973-1975, undated; 4 Folders
    This subseries consists of press releases, correspondence, reviews, and distribution agreements related to the program, THE LORD OF THE UNIVERSE (1974), in addition to an article published in Filmmaker's Newsletter by TVTV member Paul Goldsmith about the production. Also included are documents related to the work winning the Alfred I. du Pont/Columbia University Award in Broadcast Journalism.
    - LORD OF THE UNIVERSE correspondence and production documents, 1973-1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 7)
    - Filmmaker's Newsletter magazine article, 1974; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 8)
    - Alfred I. du Pont Award, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 9)
    - LORD OF THE UNIVERSE reviews, 1974, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 5: ADLAND (1974), 1973-1974, undated; 3 Folders
    This subseries consists of press materials used to promote ADLAND (1974) and TVTV in advance of the tape's completion and broadcast, clippings of reviews of the broadcast work, and a production still from the work.
    - ADLAND press materials, 1973, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 11)
    - ADLAND reviews, 1974, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 12)
    - ADLAND production still, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 6: IN HIDING (1975), 1975, undated; 3 Folders
    For the 1975 work, IN HIDING, TVTV was commissioned to interview Abbie Hoffman, who was in hiding at the time while facing federal drug charges. This subseries consists of correspondence, press releases,and documents related to the production of the work, as well as clippings of reviews and articles discussing the controversial topic and payment by public television station WNET/13 to Hoffman in exchange for the interview.
    - IN HIDING production documents, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 14)
    - IN HIDING press clippings, 1975; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 15)
    - IN HIDING press clippings, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 7: GERALD FORD'S AMERICA (1975), 1974-1975, undated; 3 Folders
    This subseries consists of contracts, correspondence, and other documents related to the production of GERALD FORD'S AMERICA, as well as production stills, and "ID Badge" photographs of TVTV crew involved in the production. Also included are reviews and articles clipped from magazines and newspapers.
    - GERALD FORD'S AMERICA production documents and correspondence, 1974-1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 17)
    - GERALD FORD'S AMERICA photographs, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 18)
    - GERALD FORD'S AMERICA press clippings, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 8: THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME (1975), 1974-1975, undated; 3 Folders
    Arranged chronologically within folders, this subseries consists of correspondence and a press release relating to the production of THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME (1975), distribution agreements drafted for the show after its initial airing, clippings of reviews and advertisements for the program, as well as letters from viewers and others responding to the original broadcast.
    - THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME production documents, 1974-1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 20)
    - THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME feedback correspondence, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 21)
    - THE GOOD TIMES ARE KILLING ME press clippings, 1975, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 9: TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL (1976), 1976, undated; 3 Folders
    Arranged chronologically, this subseries consists of correspondence relating to the funding, production, and distribution of TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL (1976), as well as correspondence after the show's airing to reviewers and others as a promotional effort. The original order for this subseries included handwritten notes indicating "pre-show" and "post-show" on two bundles of correspondence. Also included is a list of airdates for the program on PBS affiliate television stations across the United States, correspondence and documents related to equipment insurance claims, and clippings of reviews.
    - TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL correspondence and production documents, 1976, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 23)
    - TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL equipment insurance documents, 1976, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 24)
    - TVTV GOES TO THE SUPERBOWL press clippings, 1976, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 10: TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS (1976), 1975-1977, 1983, undated; 6 Folders
    Arranged chronologically, this subseries consists of correspondence and magazine clippings relating to the promotion and airing of TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS; a specially-made greeting card "invitation" to watch the original broadcast; guest lists for a related party; insurance contracts related to the production; 35mm and 2 ¼" film negatives shot during the production; press clippings of reviews; brochures and pamphlets made by the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences related to the 1975 opening of the Margaret Herrick Library; and documents related to the 1983 rebroadcast of the work.
    - TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS production documents, correspondence, and party ephemera, 1976-1977, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 26)
    - TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS insurance contracts, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 27)
    - TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS production stills negatives, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 28)
    - TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS press clippings, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 29)
    - Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences Margaret Herrick Library materials, 1975; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 30)
    - TVTV LOOKS AT THE OSCARS rebroadcast documents, 1983, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 31)
  - Subseries 11: THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL (1976), 1976-1977, undated; 4 Folders
    Arranged chronologically, this subseries consists of correspondence with critics, funders, and colleagues related to the airing, promotion, and further distribution of THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL; production and equipment insurance contracts; and press clippings of reviews.
    - THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL correspondence, 1976-1977, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 32)
    - THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL production and insurance contracts, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 33)
    - THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL press clippings 1 of 2, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 34)
    - THE BOB DYLAN HARD RAIN SPECIAL press clippings 2 of 2, 1976, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 35)
  - Subseries 12: SUPER VISION (1976), 1975-1977, undated; 5 Folders
    Arranged chronologically within folders, this subseries consists of a variety of materials generated during the planning, production, and distribution of SUPER VISION. Correspondence included reflects all stages of production on this program, from planning and taping to exhibition at the Whitney Art Museum and legal challenges from personalities lampooned in the show. Production and Public Relations documents included range from preproduction materials to publicity photographs of TVTV members. Also included is a working script and press clippings of reviews.
    - SUPER VISION correspondence, 1975-1977; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 36)
    - SUPER VISION production documents, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 37)
    - SUPER VISION publicity photographs, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 38)
    - Working script of SUPER VISION, 1975; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 39)
    - SUPER VISION press clippings, 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 40)
  - Subseries 13: THE TVTV SHOW (1977), 1975-1977, undated; 5 Folders
    Arranged chronologically within folders, this subseries consists of materials created during the planning, production, and distribution of THE TVTV SHOW (1977). Preproduction materials include handwritten notes from production meetings, drafts of scenes, technical information from NBC, receipt for deposit of the finished script with the Writers' Guild of America, and related items. Correspondence spans from the planning stages to distribution, and includes preliminary proposals; letters to colleagues, funders, and crew; and negotiations of legal and financial agreements. Also included are production stills and a draft of the script, as well as press clippings of reviews.
    - THE TVTV SHOW production notes and documents, 1976, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 41)
    - THE TVTV SHOW correspondence, 1976-1977, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 42)
    - THE TVTV SHOW publicity stills, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 43)
    - Draft script of THE TVTV SHOW (1977), 1976; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 44)
    - THE TVTV SHOW press clippings, 1977, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 45)
  - Subseries 14: Unrealized projects, 1973-1979, undated; 12 Folders
    Arranged chronologically within folders, this subseries consists of materials created in all stages of planning a large number of programs that were not ultimately produced by TVTV. These include budgets; notes for program ideas; full treatments for shows; correspondence with potential funding sources and television stations, as well as with colleagues and media outlets; and many other types of materials. Documents related to three unrealized projects have been kept separate in their original order: THE WASHINGTON BUREAU, GLASS EYE, and 1976. The bulk of this subseries contains materials for a program called PRIME TIME that spent many years in development by TVTV. The PRIME TIME materials have been separated into folders reflecting various aspects of the production, from research to planning and budgeting.
    - Unrealized projects documents and correspondence, 1973-1974; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 46)
    - Unrealized projects documents and correspondence, 1974-1979; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 47)
    - Unrealized projects documents and correspondence, 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 48)
    - THE WASHINGTON BUREAU production planning notes, 1974; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 49)
    - GLASS EYE production planning notes, 1975; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 50)
    - 1976 proposal packet, Approximately 1975; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 51)
    - PRIME TIME planning and correspondence, 1973-1977; 1 Folder (Carton 4, Folder 52)
    - PRIME TIME planning and correspondence, 1 Folder (Carton 4, Folder 53)
    - PRIME TIME production documents, receipts, and budgets, 1977, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 1, Folder 54)
    - PRIME TIME research materials, 1964, 1967, 1972, 1974-1975; 1 Folder (Carton 4, Folder 55)
    - PRIME TIME research materials, 1976-1977; 1 Folder (Carton 4, Folder 56)
    - PRIME TIME research materials, 1978-1979, undated; 1 Folder (Carton 4, Folder 57)
  - Subseries 15: Videotape raw shot logs and edit logs, 1974-1976, undated; 15 Binders
    Arranged chronologically, this subseries consists of binders used to log raw footage and edits during the production of several TVTV programs and one unidentifiable production. Binders contain between approximately 50 to approximately 250 pages of timecode logs, notes, and related information culled from raw footage and rough edits.